Guide to the Wesleyan Parleys Collection, 1924 - 1966
Wesleyan Parleys Collection, 1924 - 1966
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
1000-159
3
1, plus 17 scrapbooks
Wesleyan held an annual conference featuring scholars from around the country discussing some of the day's most controversial and important topics, including labor, crime, race, marriage, and foreign policy. The tradition of Wesleyan Parleys began in 1924 and lasted until about the early 1960s.
The Wesleyan Parleys Collection consists of seventeen scrapbooks, each devoted to a particular year's parley, and some additional material including programs and clippings. The scrapbooks include correspondence, financial information, publicity, photographs, and sometimes the text of speeches made at the parleys. Some years are not represented in the collection.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Transferred prior to 1998.
Historical Note
The Parley Committee of 1930 described the Wesleyan Parley as follows: This parley is offered to the friends, guests and students of Wesleyan with the basic assumption that we as students have no prerogative to be utterly carefree or completely cloistered from the stress and flux of affairs 'off-campus.' We believe that without scorning campus interests a student may wisely concern himself with the interwoven political and economic forces that have given his people prosperity - and in turn have given him his Alma Mater.
In a day when our government is groping through new and bewildering mazes, it seems no more than decently sporting that we students grapple these problems…Though in some campus circles this is treason, we cordially invite you to make the most of it.
Wesleyan parleys were arranged by the Parley Committee of the College Body (the student government) with secretarial assistance from the Christian Association. The Parley Committee generally consisted of four to ten students, along with faculty help until 1930. The annual conferences featured scholars from around the country discussing some of the day's most controversial and important topics, including labor, crime, race, marriage, and foreign policy. The tradition of Wesleyan Parleys began in 1924 and lasted until about the early 1960s.
Chronology List
Items marked with an asterisk (*) have accompanying scrapbooks.
1924-1925 College Life and Society
1925-1926 American College Education
1926-1927 American College Education
1927-1928 Symposium on Religion
1928-1929 Parley on War
1929-1930 *American Government and Business
1930-1931 *Parley on Crime
1931-1932 *Parley on Disarmament
1932-1933 *Parley on Marriage
1933-1934 *Parley on Race Relations
1934-1935 *Parley on Political Philosophies
1935-1936 *Parley on Labor Relations
1936-1937 *Parley on Marriage
1937-1938 *Parley on Higher Education in a Democracy
1938-1939 Parley on Inter-fraternity Relations (preliminary College Body Parley)
1938-1939 *Parley on American Foreign Policy
1939-1940 *Parley on the Political Issues in the Coming Election
1940-1941 *Parley on Marriage
1941-1942 *Parley on the Part of College Youth in the Post-War World
1946-1947 *Parley on Marriage
1947-1948 *Parley on Labor-Management Relations
1948-1949 *Parley on the United States and World Affairs
1949-1950 *Parley on Civil Liberties and American Minorities
1950-1951 Parley on Communism in a Democratic World
1952-1953 The Future of American Conservatism
1955-1956 India Today
1956-1957 The New Middle East
1958-1959 War and Peace in the Space Age
1959-1960 Parley on Social Responsibility in Labor Relations
1959-1960 The Face of American Morality
1960-1961 The South in Search of Itself
1961-1962 Government Secrecy in a Free Society
1962-1963 The Future of American Labor
1963-1964 Humor in Politics
1964-1965 Modern Dance, Music, and Theater
1965-1966 Future of the Civil Rights Movement
Collection Overview
The collection consists of seventeen scrapbooks, each devoted to a particular parley, and some additional material including programs and clippings. The scrapbooks include correspondence, financial information, publicity, photographs, and sometimes the text of speeches made at the parleys. Some years are not represented in the collection.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.); Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; Social problems--United States--History--20th century--Congresses.; United States--Social conditions--20th century--Congresses.; Crime--United States--Congresses.; Race relations --Congresses.; International relations--Congresses.; Marriage --United States --Congresses.; Labor--United States--Congresses.; Scrapbooks.
Related Material
Additional information about the Wesleyan University Parleys can be found in articles published in the Wesleyan Argus (student newspaper) and Hartford Courant around the time the parleys took place.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1: Scrapbooks
  When the full text of a speech is included, this is indicated.
  - Parley on American Government and Business, February 28-March 1, 1930 (Volume 1)
    Volume includes correspondence, publicity, invitations, and expenses.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Oswald Garrison Villard, Government and Business in the Court of Domestic Relations
      - Myron W. Watkins, Grounds and Limits of Public Control of Business
      - Morris Hillquit, Growing Social and Business Functions of Government
      - Thomas J. Doherty, Lobbying and the Tariff
      - Peter H. Odegard, Pressure Politics
      - Raymond Leslie Buell, Imperialism: Our Invisible Empire
      - John T. Flynn, Can Business Rule Itself?
  - Parley on Crime, December 5-December 6, 1930 (Volume 2)
    Volume includes preliminary planning materials, correspondence, invitations, expenses, and clippings.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Dr. William Healy, Psychological and Social Origins of Crime
      - Everett W. Duvall, Juvenile Delinquency
      - George W. Kirchwey, Crime and Penal Reform
        Includes full text of speech.
      - Jack Black, Crime and the Criminal
      - Clarence Darrow, Crime and the Criminal Court
  - Parley on Disarmament, December 4-December 5, 1931 (Volume 3)
    Volume includes correspondence, publicity, invitations, lecture bureau pamphlets, and expenses. The volume also contains a student poll on disarmament and a photograph of Rear Admiral Sims.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Rear Admiral William S. Sims, U.S.N., Disarmament - The Limitation of Armaments and Freedom of the Seas
      - Frank H. Simonds, Obstacles of Disarmament
      - Harry W. Laidler, class of 1907, Roads to World Peace
      - Frederick J. Libby, Disarmament and National Security
      - Rear Admiral Charles L. Hussey, U.S.N. Disarmament
      - President Harry A. Garfield, The Future of Disarmament
  - Parley on Marriage, December 8-December 9, 1932 (Volume 4)
    Volume includes Parley regulations, publicity, clippings, correspondence, expenses, and lecture bureau pamphlets.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Gladys H. Groves, The Feminine Side of It
      - Professor Erdman Harris, The Masculine Side of It
      - Father John M. Cooper, The Church and Modern Marriage Problems
      - Dr. William B. Terhune, Mental Adjustments in Marital Life
      - Rev. Roy B. Chamberlin, class of 1909, Youth Prepares for Marriage
      - Margaret Sanger, The Case for Birth Control
      - Dr. Clarence G. Campbell, The Modern Approach to Marriage
  - Parley on Race Relations, February 8-February 9, 1934 (Volume 5)
    Volume includes clippings, correspondence, invitations, and lecture bureau pamphlets.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Dr. F.E. Auhagen, Principals of the National Socialist Program
      - Rabbi Abraham J. Feldman, Hitlerism and the Jew
      - Dr. Walter F. White, The Negro and American Civilization
      - Sir Frederick Whyte, K.C.S.I., Chinese Aspects of the Manchukuo Situation
      - Dr. Roy Hidemichi Akagi, Japanese Aspects of the Manchukuo Situation
      - Kirby Page, The Problem of Race Relations
  - Parley on Political Philosophies, December 5-December 7, 1934 (Volume 6)
    Volume includes correspondence, planning and arrangement information, invitations, and lecture bureau pamphlets. It also includes the platform of the Socialist Labor Party of America.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Professor Francis Coker and Dr. Bruno Roselli, Fascism
      - Max Eastman, Communism
      - Horace M. Kallen, The Individual and the Modern State
      - Mr. V.F. Calverton, Culture and Communism
      - H. Gordon Hayes, The New Deal
      - Professor Nathan Isaacs, Free Private Enterprise
      - Professor H.U. Faulkner and Col. Henry Breckenridge, Individualistic Democracy
      - Mr. Norman Thomas, Socialism
      - Mr. Scott Nearing, Communism and America
      - Mr. Seward Collins, Fascism
      - Hon. Hamilton Fish, Individualistic Democracy
      - Hon. Charles M. Bakewell, Social Responsibility under Individualistic Democracy
      - Dr. Harry Laidler, Social Responsibility under Socialism
  - Parley on Labor Relations, December 4-December 6, 1935 (Volume 7)
    Volume includes correspondence, lecture bureaus, and invitations. The text of many of the speeches is included. Also includes photos of Granville Hicks, Charles P. Howard, Gilbert H. Montague, and David Lasser.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Labor and the Law with Ainslee Slodden, presiding. Featuring Arthur Garfield Hays, Liberal Lawyer and Henry Clifton, Conservative Lawyer
        Includes text of Hay's speech.
      - The Place of White Collar and Professional Workers with James L. McConaughy, Jr., presiding. Featuring John Goss, Industrialist and Granville Hicks, Economist and Author
        Includes text of speeches by both Goss and Hicks.
      - The Issue of Company Unions, Craft Unions, and Industrial Unions with J. Kemper Burton, presiding. Featuring John P. Frey, Craft Unionist; Charles P. Howard, Industrial Unionist; and David Saposs, Company Unionist
        Includes text of speeches by Frey, Howard, and Saposs.
      - The Industrial Disputes Act with Richard Harfst, presiding. Featuring Gilbert Montague, Conservative opposed to the act; Abraham J. Muste, Radical opposed to the act; and David Saposs
        Includes text of speeches by Montague, Muste, and Saposs.
      - The Issue of a Labor Party with Burton C. Hallowell, presiding. Featuring J.P. Frey, representing A.F. of L. position and Robert Minor, Radical in favor of a labor party
        Includes text of speeches by both Frey and Minor.
      - The Issue of Social Insurance and Relief with Kenneth R. Andrews, presiding. Featuring Rulon Williamson, Conservative and David Lasser, Socialist
        Includes text of speech by Lasser.
      - The Place of Labor under a Socialized and under a Capitalistic State with Herman Muehsam, presiding. Featuring Scott Nearing, Radical and Professor O. G. Saxon, Conservative
        Includes text of speeches by both Nearing and Saxon.
  - Parley on Marriage, December 3-December 4, 1936 (Volume 8)
    Volume includes correspondence, news releases, invitations, programs, finances, and lecture bureau pamphlets. Also includes two photos of Katharine H. (Mrs. Thomas N.) Hepburn and a photo of Norman E. Himes, and pamphlets of varying opinions on birth control.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - V. F. Calverton, The Crisis in Contemporary Marriage
      - Professor Hornell Hart, Science and Sexual Ethics
        Includes text of Hart's speech.
      - Oliver M. Butterfield, Preparation for Marriage
      - Rabbi Sidney E. Goldstein, State Responsibility in the Matter of Marriage and Family Life
        Includes text of Goldstein's speech.
      - Mrs. Grace Loucks Elliott, Marriage and Maturity
      - Dr. Ernest R. Groves, The Masculine Side of It
      - Mrs. Ernest R. Groves, The Feminine Side of It
      - Dr. S. Ralph Harlow, How to Be Happy tho Married in this Generation
        Includes text of Harlow's speech.
      - Dr. Harry Bone, Some Contributions of Clinical Psychology to Problems of Normal Marriage
      - Professor Albert P. Van Dusen, Essentials of Marital Stability
      - Mrs. Katharine H. Hepburn, The Case for Birth Control
      - Professor Norman E. Himes, Family Limitation
  - Parley on Higher Education in a Democracy, March 10-March 11, 1938 (Volume 9)
    Volume includes correspondence, news releases, invitations, finances, and cancelled checks.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Henry M. Wriston and George S. Counts, The Function of the Privately Endowed College in a Democracy
      - Thomas J. Dodd, Christian Gauss, and Eduard C. Lindeman, Education and the State
        Includes text of Dodd's speech.
      - Robert Lamb, Intellectual Freedom
      - Herbert E. Hawkes, Generalization Requirements
      - Molly Yard, David Dellinger, and Jerome Davis, New Organizations in Education
      - Olin F. McCormick and Julius Hochman, What Faces the College-Trained Man after College in Business and Labor
      - Charles Hubbard Judd and William Allan Neilson, Confusion in an American Education
  - Parley on American Foreign Policy, March 8-March 10, 1939 (Volume 10)
    Volume includes correspondence, news releases, financial information, lists of guests, lecture bureau pamphlets, and a Chairman of the Parley committee report. The following photographs are also included: one photo each of Carleton Beals, Edwin Borchard, Nathaniel Peffer, George N. Shuster, Mrs. Louise Leonard Wright; two photos of Smedley D. Butler; three photos of Gerald P. Nye; a photo of O.E. Stone, George N. Shuster, and Nathaniel Peffer; and a photo of five unknown men.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - A.A. Berle, Jr. and Edwin Borchard, A Community of Nations in the Western Hemisphere
        Includes text of speech by Berle.
      - Gerald P. Nye and Louise Leonard Wright, Collective Security versus Isolation
      - Carleton Beals and Smedley D. Butler, American Foreign Policy in a Post-Munich World
      - Frederick L. Schuman and Raymond Leslie Buell, American Foreign Policy and the British Empire
      - George Fielding Eliot, The Ramparts We Watch
      - George Hubbard Blakeslee, The United States in the Far East
      - Hubert Herring, The Two Americas
      - Nathaniel Peffer and George N. Shuster, America Looks to the East and to the West
  - Parley on the Political Issues in the Coming Election, March 8-9, 1940 (Volume 11)
    Volume includes correspondence, news releases, invitations, finances, and lecture bureau pamphlets. Also includes photographs and biographies of the speakers and abstracts of their addresses and discussions.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Vito Marcantonio and Merwin K. Hart, The Labor, Business, and Government Triangle
        Includes text of speeches by Marcantoni and Hart.
      - Clarence A. Hathaway, The Communists' Future Political Objectives
        Includes text of Hathaway's speech.
      - Harry W. Laidler, The Socialists' Future Political Objectives
        Includes text of Laidler's speech.
      - Len Decaux and John J. Egan, The Outlook of Organized Labor
        Includes text of speeches by Decaux and Egan.
      - Harold Brayman, A Political Observer Views Washington
      - Ernest K. Lindley, The Capital Looks at the Nation
      - Saul Forbes Rae, The Public Opinion Polls in the Coming Election
        Includes text of Rae's speech.
      - Edward L. Bernays, The Public Opinion Polls: A Critical Analysis
        Includes text Bernays's speech.
      - Senator Claude Pepper and Congressman Dewey Short, The Democratic and Republican Outlooks for 1940
        Includes text of speeches by Pepper and Short.
      - Max Lerner, The American Way in the Future
        Includes text of Lerner's speech.
  - Parley on Marriage, February 27-28, 1941 (Volume 12)
    Volume includes correspondence, news releases, programs, finances, guest lists, and lecture bureau pamphlets.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Dr. Henry Pratt Fairchild, The Challenge of Marriage
      - Mrs. Katherine Hepburn, In Defense of Birth Control
      - Professor Joseph Kirk Folsolm, The Crisis of Contemporary Marriage
      - Professor Joseph Kirk Folsolm, The Crisis of Contemporary Marriage
      - Amram Scheinfeld, Comic Strips and Chromosomes
        Includes abstract of Scheinfeld's speech.
      - Dr. L. Foster Wood, Marriage and the Churches
      - Dr. Ira Wile, Mental Adjustments in Marital Life
      - Judge John Warren Hill, Predicting Success or Failure in Marriage
      - Dr. Valeria Hopkins Parker, A Physician Views the Problems of Marriage
      - Margaret Mead, Marriage Patterns, Primitive and Modern
      - Harry Elmer Barnes, Marriage in a Changing Society
  - Parley on the Part of College Youth in the Post-War World, March 1-2, 1942 (Volume 13)
    Volume includes correspondence, news releases, finances, guests and accommodation information, and lecture bureau pamphlets.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Professor Carl Joachim Friedrich, The Challenge of the Post-War World for College Students
      - Sinclair Lewis, The Problems of Reconstruction
      - Dr. Mordecai Ezekiel, The Problem of Maintaining Full Employment after the War
      - Ralph E. Flanders, Design for Living in America
      - Raymond Moley, Imagine Independence in a Totalitarian World
  - Parley on Marriage, March 13-14, 1947 (Volume 14)
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Dr. Benjamin Simon, All Marriages are Made in Heaven
      - Dr. Abraham Stone, Modern Trends in Planned Parenthood
      - Dr. John H. Mariano, Tendencies of Modern Marriages
      - Dr. Valeria Hopkins Parker, The Physician Views the Problems of Marriage
      - Dr. S. Ralph Harlow, Religion's Place in Marriage
      - Dr. Harry A. Overstreet, Marriage and the Family in a Changing Society
      - Father George B. Ford, Marriage as an Enduring Institution
  - Parley on Labor-Management Relations, March 11-March 12, 1948 (Volume 15)
    Volume includes correspondence, biographical sketches and pictures, news releases, and a photo of Senator Flanders, Senator Ives, and J. Raymond Walsh
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Men Versus Machines, with Professor Robert R. R. Brooks, moderator. Featuring Boris Shiskin (labor) and Travis Whitney (management)
      - The Villain of High Prices - Wages or Profits? with Senator Ralph Flanders, moderator. Featuring Tilford Dudley (labor) and Dr. Alfred P. Haake (management)
      - Henry Laidler, Ethics in Labor- Management Relations
      - J. Raymond Walsh, Labor in Politics
      - John Driscoll, Fundamentals of a Strike
      - The Pro and Con of the Taft-Hartley Bill, with Senator Irving M. Ives, moderator. Featuring Lee Pressman (labor) and Virgil B. Day (management)
  - Parley on the United States and World Affairs, March 10-March 11, 1949 (Volume 16)
    Volume includes programs, suggestions, correspondence, news releases, finances, information about guests and accommodations, and a series of 14 photos taken during the Parley event.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - Norman Thomas and Edward C. Acheson, US in World Economic Readjustment
      - Arthur Hummel and David Gordon, US and China
      - Chitoshi Yanaga, US and the Future Role of Japan
      - Frederick C. Barghoorn, US and Russia
      - Oscar Schachter and Thomas C. P. Martin, Beyond Nationalism
  - Parley on Civil Liberties and American Minorities, March 23-March 24, 1950 (Volume 17)
    Volume includes a 1950 Parley History, correspondence with speakers, publicity, correspondence with delegates, and a financial report.
    - Speakers and Topics
      - The Honorable Chester Bowles and Mr. Robert T. Collins, What is the Position of American Minorities?
        Includes text of speech by Collins.
      - Mr. Alexander F. Miller, The South
      - Professor Willmoore Kendall, Minorities and Communism
      - Dean Eugene S. Wilson, Discrimination in Colleges and Universities
      - Congressman Adam Clayton Powell, Discrimination in the Economic Sphere
      - Mr. Patrick Malin and Professor Roscoe C. Martin, How Will the Position of American Minorities Change?
- Series 2: Additional Material
  - Programs
    - 1924-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1940-1942, 1947, 1949-1951, 1956, 1959, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Parley on Communism clippings, March 1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous parley materials, 1950-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)